Perfect. Okay. So, shall we start? Um
I have two sutta passages that might be
interesting to talk about.
And the the first one is is about jati,
about uh
birth or
being born, how I like to translate it.
And the second is is about bhava,
um which usually usually is a translated
as um being or existence
or becoming.
So, maybe I just read the first the first
maybe I just read the first the first
bit about jati.
And
it's from the
uh
Majjhima Nikaya 9, Sammāditthi Sutta.
Because, friends, a noble disciple
understands being born, jati,
and the appearance of being born,
the cessation of being born, and the
practice leading to the cessation of
being born, to that extent a noble
disciple is of right view,
is his view straight,
is he endowed with unwavering confidence
in regard to Dhamma,
has he arrived at this true Dhamma?
And what, friend, is being born?
What is the appearance of being born?
What's the cessation of being born?
What is the practice leading to the
cessation of being born?
The being born of those and those beings
into this and that class of beings,
their birth, descent, production,
manifestation of the aggregates,
obtaining of the fears of the
spheres, this, friend, is called being born.
this, friend, is called being born.
With the appearance of bhava is the
appearance of being born.
With the cessation of power, is the
cessation of being born.
Just this noble eightfold path
is the practice leading to the cessation
of being born. That is right view up to
right composure.
So, what's your question?
The question is how to
correctly understand being born because
I think there are
a lot of different views about this and
what's what strikes me most about this
passage is that it says
uh
birth of being born is the manifestation
of the aggregates and the obtaining of
the spheres, ayatana spheres, ayatana
and
I think when people usually hear hear
the word birth, they
they think about like
a baby coming out of the womb.
So, but
like parturition and
I think it's not that it's not what's
what's being uh
aimed at here. Um
because the manifestation of the
aggregates and
the obtaining of the spheres for contact
or for experience
it cannot be observed from a
third-person perspective. It can only
be recognized from the inside.
And yeah.
yeah.
Yeah, well, the most important thing
there practically speaking that you you
want to understand is that when it says
understanding of being born, uh it's
something that's still enduring right
here and now.
So, it's not the the birth event from
the past
which you haven't even, you know, you
certainly were not witnessing it.
Although you were being born, you don't
you have no memory of it.
It's the recognition of the through the
current being, you know that birth is
enduring there.
Because the senses are enduring there.
The ayatanas are there. Thus the birth
is there. So if you understand that, you
have understood bhava. If you understand
bhava, you have understood the birth.
And that's why the right view is tied
with it. It's not like, oh, you have
figured out how you came out of the womb
or something biologically. No, it's
understanding that on on on the on a
presently speaking, your birth endures
there because you're still alive with a
functioning senses.
So the reason why this is practically
relevant is yeah,
your whole life, your whole existence,
your whole bhava
is equally determined by the existence
of your physical organs. They were born,
produced in this world, came into this
being so to speak, and are enduring
there randomly, completely out of out of
the sphere of your control, and it's
even inconceivable for you how would
existence be without the senses.
Literally, it's inseparable from it. Yet
you have you have no say in it.
So you truly if you truly understand
birth, you have abandoned bhava or or a
great deal of it.
Which means you have abandoned the
ownership of it as well.
So just the recognition of that
physical material necessity that has
been produced through birth, that's
still endures there as a basis for your
your existence.
And that's something that's that's
that's that you will never be able to
own or repossess or take charge of.
So what does it what does it mean that
um birth is is said to have bhava as as
condition.
Well, it means that fundamentally the
the whole um
you haven't been freed from ignorance.
So, you're still bound to the same five
aggregates that keep getting reproduced
here and there through which your bhava
excels even more.
It's a vicious circle. It's not there is
a being first that fuels your birth.
Yeah, bhava is That's what I mean, it's
mutually determined.
Because you're not free from bhava now,
if you die, you you haven't freed
yourself from the five aggregates. Means
you're going to find the repro-
reproduced form elsewhere.
form elsewhere.
Bound by that bhava that you haven't
freed yourself from.
And when you find the reproduced form
elsewhere, you keep acting out of it
with that ignorance that kept you bound
to it. And then you're maintaining your
bhava or even bringing even more bhava
to fulfillment.
Which then results in even worse rebirth
later on.
Cuz you have sensual bhava, material
immaterial bhava, all these layers that
people would be adding up to it.
But either way bhava is there, which is
why you are constantly or rather
perpetually still wandering in within
the framework of samsara.
Which is your five aggregates.
Okay, I think the the next the next
sutta passage that's
uh
fits quite nicely.
This is bhava sutta it's called and it's
the Buddha speaking with Ananda.
And Ananda asked the Buddha,
"Bhava bhava venerable sir said,
to what extent now, venerable sir, is
there bhava?"
And the Buddha answers,
"If Ananda, there were no action, comma,
showing results in the realm of
sensuality, in the realm of form,
in the realm of no form,
would sensuality bhava, form bhava, no
form bhava be discerned.
No, venerable sir.
Thus, Ananda, action is the field,
consciousness the seed,
and craving the moisture.
The intention and aspiration of beings
hindered by non-knowledge, avidya, and
fettered by craving is established in a
lower, in a middling, in a refined
realm. Thus, there is in the future the
Thus, there is in the future the
production of bhava again.
Thus, Ananda, is there bhava?
Yeah, well, that's exactly what I said.
What sutta is that?
That is
Anguttara Nikaya 3:37.
Uh 77, sorry.
Yeah, so that so that's what I I was
saying in the beginning, practically
speaking, either you look at bhava, you
look at birth, you're basically you want
to be seeing the same principle, the
same thing,
which is fundamentally the nature of
that presently enduring phenomena as
anicca, as anatta, and thoroughly
develop that. Now, obviously,
most of us you cannot just stick with
one theme constantly. Sooner or later
you you run out. So, whether you
approach it through bhava or
paticcasamuppada or jati specifically or
salayatana, you want to be doing the
same thing, just finding basically an
inspiration from all these different
angles. But it does come down to repetition of
But it does come down to repetition of
that work.
To like I'm doing that bhava pretty much
through understanding and repetition of
those reflections
of non-ownership and so on.
Dissatisfactoriness, uh disease, inherent disease in in lack
uh disease, inherent disease in in lack
of ownership of basically your own
foundations.
So, could you say that
bhava is, in principle,
this mutual dependence of consciousness
on phenomena, on nama-rupa? Well,
theoretically, but practically that
you're never going to see it like that.
You cannot step outside of your
experience and see these two sticks that
support each other as your bhava cuz you
are one of them at a time.
So, the only way to understand this is
to practically undo it.
And that is important to emphasize
because often
people who have a sort of inclination
towards intellectual understanding,
which is, you know,
as good as any other way to start.
Well, the problem with that is you tend
to overdo it. So, then your intellectual
ideas, you start assuming as if they
factually stand for what bhava is and
amarupa determination is, but that's
impossible. Because that would require you to step
Because that would require you to step
outside of yourself to see it in such
manner, and that that cannot be done.
So, you use the intellectual ideas to
set you in a direction, but then it has
to come down to you restraining yourself
from giving in to that side and focusing
on maintaining the right order as in,
"No, this bhava right here right now, my
existence as a whole, that is first. And
I must not think about it by abandoning
it. If I think about it, bhava, it must
be done within this currently
experienced as a whole that that
exists." So, that's what I mean. The only way to
So, that's what I mean. The only way to
understand it is to actually undo it.
Free yourself from bhava, you have full
understanding of bhava.
Any other thing you you mustn't forget
that it's going to be on the
intellectual level, and it can be sort
of easily you could easily fall into
assumption and take that intellectual idea as
and take that intellectual idea as
factual understanding of bhava or at
least pertaining to that understanding
of bhava. But yet, practically, your
bhava hasn't diminished, made no
difference to it, which means there is
no understanding of bhava. Doesn't
matter how pleasing your idea might be. So, um So, um
to
discern bhava in my experience
bhava in my experience
now um
would that be um
um
synonymous with discerning
uh greed, hatred, or
delusion I uh
um
It could if it leads you to it, so to
speak, but I don't know what greed,
aversion, delusion mean to you as ideas.
So, I can't say yes because when you
think about greed, it might be abstract.
So, it will certainly not stand for the
present enduring Baba as a whole.
What you want to think basically is find
a basis. Like ask yourself, why do you
want to understand Baba? What is the
relevance there?
Why is it relevant understanding Baba?
What should result in?
Like here and now, not in 10 years, in
15 years, tomorrow. Now, if I were to
tell you you must understand Baba or if
you were to think that, why? Why would
you need to understand Baba? What do you
think? Uh to understand
the what is meant by its cessation um
But what why is that relevant? Why is
understanding cessation of Baba relevant
to you?
Why does it matter
That
um image is
uh associated with
what it means to be free from
suffering in a way or or or or or or or
or or or or or or or or or or or or or
or or or or or or or Sure. So, freedom
from suffering is what matters to you,
which is why you want to understand
bhava?
So, where does the suffering happen?
Where does it occur?
If it were to occur, where would it be?
Where would you suffer?
Would you suffer as an idea?
Would your suffering be just an idea?
Would it be an experience as a whole?
Would you be affected by it?
It would be as emotional on a
on a level of Exactly. So, it would be
on the level of the feeling of the
experience as a whole. If it's
suffering, it's something you cannot
remain indifferent to.
So, that's where you understand your
bhava. There is no reason to do something else
There is no reason to do something else
and understand it elsewhere because as
you said it yourself, that's why
understanding of bhava is relevant
because freedom from suffering is
relevant, which means you don't go
elsewhere where you don't suffer to
understand bhava that will somehow
return for your freedom from suffering.
Then you're just revolving around the
idea of bhava.
So, that's what's meant by concrete
thinking whereby you show, you think,
you contemplate, but don't allow
yourself to go into abstract.
And that happens when you forget or you
lose the context of your current
situation and the currently enduring
feeling, which is always the basis for
your practice. I said that many times in
my talks as in the sutras. I think some
kind of I cannot remember exactly
number, but it says things will converge
on feelings. Feeling is the converging
point for your experience, basically.
for your experience, basically.
So, you want to understand bhava, you
understand the nature of presently
enduring feeling. Why? Because that's
already what bhava is. That's what being
is.
And that's the problem with approaching
it philosophically is it already starts
as an idea in philosophy.
Even in in phenomenology and
existentialism, when they they started
with like a um
investigation of being as Heidegger
would say, but inevitably had to divorce
it and it sort of became like an
abstraction. And sure enough, Heidegger
in his later work mystified himself. It
became the being, you know. You can't
even express it in the words anymore.
Because it's Unless you have the right
context to know where you must stick to
and stay on when you do a contemplation,
it will take you into this idea that you
will now assume it stands for the being
while factually it doesn't. Because if
your understanding of that idea were
right, you would be free from being here
and now, which means you would be
becoming anagami, free from sensual
being altogether.
So, that's how you measure your being by
diminishing of
the pressure of your desire that's
expressed in regard to craving
uh on the level of that converging point
of your own feeling.
So, that's it's it's a useful thing to
to keep in mind like whichever way you
were to approach the suttas, like
whether you read the sutta and I want to
think about jati as I said or
you you must think it on the basis of
the concrete situation of you here and
now.
So, what sometimes people do is like
they're so focused on here and now, they
dismiss their thinking.
And then they start to spiritualize and
mystify here and now, just be present
and aware.
Or people forget here and now and then
go completely lost get completely lost
in their thoughts.
But actually, those things are not
mutually exclusive. You can learn It
just takes effort and discipline
how to concretely thinking your current
situation. And that's where your
thoughts cease to misconceive what's
what basically enduring there and start
to correspond to it more and more
accurately. And that's where things become apparent.
And that's where things become apparent.
The only time things become apparent is
when things were there, but you were not
seeing them.
You wouldn't say something becomes
apparent when suddenly appears for you.
No, it becomes apparent when you read
this Oh, it was there, but I haven't
seen it. Now it's apparent that it was
there.
So so the concrete thinking should
enable you
to while you not lose the mindfulness of
your current context, recollecting this
composure of your situation, to think
about various factors of that
experience. Whether it's the presently
enduring being of this of the central
kind or converging point of feelings on
account of which suffering can still
pressure you or jati, whatever way you
want to take it, you want to see it
as a phenomenon here and now, not in as
an idea or and then engage with it on
the level of that idea. You might have
to start as an idea, but you want to
find that idea apparent here and now,
not like you go where the idea is and
then engage with it over there.
That will just result in more ideas.
Uh with regards to the sutra that that
refers to
um jati as
uh descending
uh uh in brackets from the womb. Um
I mean this might be
taking it to uh abstracting it, but um
so if I were to relate that to now my
experience, um
yeah, I I I I would interpret it as as
as meaning this this
this this
uh body that that that was
um
was born into a womb uh
was born yeah, was descended into a
womb. Um Um
I
I'm appropriating um
and so by understanding
so by understanding
my appropriation of of
this this
body I'm coming to understand jati um
I I I
in the context of that particular suta
um Well, yeah, but like what you want to
see is understand not specifically how
coming out of womb happens. That is
irrelevant. That's not what this is
about. It's just a general description of how
It's just a general description of how
this current form has originated because
the being was still there.
So you want to dwell on the nature, like
what is the nature of coming out of womb
in case of a baby?
Did you Did you have any say in how you
going to come out? In when you going to
come out?
if I don't um
identify with
this body, then then I'm not
identifying with jati. If that makes
Well, yes, sure. Sure. Yeah, you can say
it by by not taking up this body, then
you you cease to own that production of
this body and you won't be taking
another one.
However, identification is not in the
level of your choice. You can't just
choose to not identify. Identification
is the result
of underlying causes that you haven't
uprooted. So it's a symptom of the problem, not
So it's a symptom of the problem, not
the problem.
And that's why I keep saying you must
discern a nature as underlying causes,
like in the true sense, like
uncontrollable uncontrollable and
ownable. Applying to you right here,
right now. So even when you think
abstractly about
your actual physical coming out of your
mother's womb,
you want to think about it at the this
that still applies to you now. That's
how you are right here, right now,
thinking about that.
So, that kind of material sort of events
in the world, basically that's what
sense organs are.
And you have absolutely no say in that.
You haven't had say in the birth of
those things, so how could you possibly
have say in the ending of those things?
Inconceivable. And most importantly,
that whole contemplation is applicable
to you here and now, and you should be
feeling it if you're doing it rightly.
Probably feeling it as as as a form of
uneasiness.
Cuz that's the direct result of seeing a
nature correctly. Anicca dukkha.
So, the fact that a random body being
born in the world
is something you cannot be indifferent
towards because of your own ignorance
should be a problem for you.
The fact that that birth applies to you
because you don't know how to not own it
should be a problem to you.
So, you realize it's not about
understanding the birth and how you come
out, it's about understanding that
gratuitous ownership of it.
And I'm doing that, and then you don't
care how you came out and and what happened.
how you came out and and what happened.
All you know is it doesn't concern you
anymore. That means you have stopped
identifying with it.
Colloquially speaking.
Then may I like to come back to this um
metaphor that is given in the in the
sutta and Uh-huh. where it says that uh
and Uh-huh. where it says that uh
action or kamma is the field
and consciousness the seed
and craving the moisture.
And um frankly, I can't I can't really
make much of that of that simile except
I can I can reformulate it a bit and
say, "Okay, so what it says is that
that the the seed of of consciousness
moistured by craving
grows in a field of action." But
But
and the sutta says, "Okay, that is how
there is bhava."
Mhm. But I don't know what it's what it
But I don't know what it's what it
means. I cannot see directly.
Yeah, so so you want to basically find
something more practical that can stand
for that principle such as
your current level of your bhava is
kamma bhava. I I presume you're not free
from sensuality, otherwise you wouldn't
be asking me these questions.
So
what is the greatest, the easiest, the
simplest exemplification of sensuality?
It's essential desire.
So that's the can be used as a
representative of sensual being.
Obviously, sensual being is any being,
any existence on account of being bound
with the senses, not necessarily just
sensual craving,
but the most obvious example is the
sensual craving.
So
and you know that already
based on your previous experience before
you were a monk, the more you want
things, the more you end up wanting
other things later. So the more you
cultivate your desire, the more the
desire grows.
The more you give in to acting out of
desire, the harder the desire will pressure you
the harder the desire will pressure you
later on.
And giving in to acting out of desire
it's exactly that action that keeps
fueling the already existing
that level of that sensual being.
So that's why it's not a static thing.
It's something you maintain through your
action. And that's what I said even
before you enter the sutta, when you are
born you keep acting in whatever
whatever you are born, using whatever
you were given in that birth.
And unknowingly you are already
expanding and proliferating and fueling
and feeding that being further it grows.
But sure, if you start practicing sense
restraint, even even without any
knowledge of Dhamma, if you are simply
abstaining from sensual desire, you are
now preventing
you are not adding moisture so to speak
to that seed.
So it will not grow as much.
That's why even like being being
restrained and celibate is a meritorious
in itself as the Buddha would describe.
And people who
who live their life in such manner will
have a better rebirth next because
being has diminished from that coarser
sense and became more refined and lofty.
So their next production of the body so
to speak will be in in a corresponding
realm. But practically speaking, acting out of
But practically speaking, acting out of
desire fuels desire. Acting out of being
fuels the being.
So the fact that you are not indifferent
to when you act out of out of the
pressure of sense of sense pull, sense
organs pulling you towards something,
means you're already bound with that
base. And that's what it means that
consciousness is there established upon
it like a seed.
So it will proliferate with giving in to
that pressure. But if you don't give in
to the pressure, it cannot proliferate.
But I think the problem you might have
is I have a feeling you're still trying
to understand these things from the
external point of view.
You want them to fit perfectly
on the level of the abstract idea.
And it's impossible to see those things
like that because you are the one who is
conscious.
So you can only see it by undoing it
here and now.
And it's a matter of choice for you.
You choose like you have the idea of it
and that's fine, but you also have a
choice to not give in to pursuing on the
level of idea and try and rework it here
and now.
But you would probably more often be
choosing to give in to the idea and want
to have it explained and cleared and
fixed in order to apply it here and now.
But those are two different things
actually.
And I know I can relate to that.
So yes, you can think about the
consciousness and you should, but don't
mistake that to be the actual factual
phenomenon of consciousness that that
that endures in your experience here and
now cuz you can't think that.
cuz you can't think that.
You can only undo it.
Undo its support.
Stop cultivating that field where that
cultivating that field where that
consciousness will grow and then it will
it will eventually cease.
Cease to exist there paired with it.
So how to undo it?
Well, this is how it starts. So you you
start by recognizing where is the
converging point? Even for your ideas by
the way.
I'm sure you feel pressure to understand
uh the similarity of conscious and where
do you feel that pressure here and now?
On the level of your feeling.
And you give in to the pressure means
you give in to the craving of your
feeling for the sake of not maintaining
for the sake of not maintaining
supposedly craving in your feeling.
Because craving is the moisture.
So, you undo it by not acting out of
craving on the level of your thoughts,
speech, and action.
And that includes figuring out the
simile that the Buddha gave that you
want to understand through your craving.
So, it's not that I'm saying you must
stop thinking,
but I'm saying you must stop thinking
out of craving.
And that takes time to learn.
And that's the problem. Sometimes people
get a hint of that. Oh, craving is the
problem, but they blame the thinking.
And that's often when you hear the
teachers and whatever traditions and so,
ah, just stop thinking, stop thinking.
Because it's like what Janavada would
say, throwing the baby with the
bathwater. Instead of wait, I need to keep the
Instead of wait, I need to keep the
baby. So, I need to keep the thinking,
throw away the craving.
But you don't know how to do that, so
you throw away the whole thing and you
think you dealt with craving, but then
that becomes rooted in craving. Cuz you
are not differentiating between craving
and your thoughts.
Or thoughts infected with craving and
thoughts not infected with craving.
You just dismiss the whole thing, which
means craving goes underground and now
you can't even see it.
So, when you have thoughts,
contemplations, basically
try and maintain the perspective on how
you what feeling is enduring while
you're thinking it and whether you're
pressured towards thinking it
or you are kind of in control of those
thoughts and could just stop thinking if
you want to.
Or is it more pressuring, urgent, in
which case you know the craving is
involved. That's why in the like if if you master
That's why in the like if if you master
this like the five ways of thinking,
the Buddha would say, craving will
completely diminish and you can think
whatever you want and you cannot think
whatever you don't want to think. You
would be in charge of your thoughts.
Not because you learn how to manipulate
the thoughts, it's because you clear
them of craving. That's what was
preventing you before to be in charge of
them. Cuz craving have charge over you.
Cuz craving have charge over you.
And then you were acting like a puppet
towards what that craving wanted.
So that's how you would undo the baba or
understand consciousness and freedom.
Or provide the moisture in the fertile
ground. Cuz if there is no craving, like in case
Cuz if there is no craving, like in case
of an arahant, any action that is done,
it will not result in proliferation of
consciousness and being.
Cuz the the domain nourishment the
nutrient is gone.
So that's why arahant can still act
without any implications or
repercussions. Cuz there is no being involved.
The thing called how all these answers
which you were giving you, you know,
it's like a big principle. So actually
whatever question you ask, it's pretty
much the same answer.
It's like you can it would be stupid to
ask a new question because it would be
okay, I know the answer.
Well, it's it's you you're not going to
get like everything boils down to
anicca, dukkha, and the experience of
anatta. Literally all the suttas it will
boil down to this one thing, one
statement. But it's seeing that same principle
But it's seeing that same principle
through all these different angles,
that's what practice is. Because as I
said, it's virtually impossible for your
mind to just stick to one way. I I
theoretically it's possible, but it's
not going to work in practice.
But you want to be
finding these things, not just applying
with the answer, oh yes, this is anicca,
this is dukkha. Each time you you start
your contemplation through whichever
way, you want to discern these same
apparent things in that contemplation.
So that's the drilling and he trains
himself thus, he trains himself thus as
the Buddha would say.
So, you are repeating the same thing
through all these different angles and
and and everywhere, left and right, all
range of motion.
Cuz that's the whole point. You want to
arrive at the same conclusion not
theoretically, but each time see it as
an apparent thing.
Cuz yes, that's exactly why many people
would Oh, yeah, okay, I got the sense of
anicca. I understood it, you know,
relatively clearly, and they think
that's it.
So, now whenever I come across any
problem or anything I haven't
understood, I just paste
this information of anicca that I picked
up from the suttas. I just say, "Oh,
that's anicca." See anicca and just
repeat to myself as a mantra until I
forget about a problem and see, I freed
myself from anicca. No.
Each time you need to rework your way
right through the problem and find that
anicca apparent. And if you did find it,
it will cease to cause you suffering,
that problem, while it is still there.
Because truly understanding anicca
is what frees you from that dukkha of of
of implicit dukkha of anicca.
Not seeing anicca is why it is felt as
dukkha.
So, every single time, whatever it is
that you think or approach, you can take
that as the as the end, as the goal.
Oh, okay. So, on on these terms, let me
discern that phenomenon of anicca.
An inability, changeability, subject to
change, impermanent, whichever way you
want to translate it. Translate it in
every way cuz it give you also different
angles to approach it.
But you want to see it enduring as such.
Not just impose your thought over it. As
As
uh the intention, for example, like
that I'm
I find myself um
I don't know, yeah, lying
in bed at night or something or yeah,
and there is um
a a realization that this is the
intention in my mind or yeah. Then then Then then
um
yeah, you're reflecting on
the nature of
What intention? Give me an example.
I I yeah, I suppose
what I'm asking is like yeah, so it's
like the this this this practice you describe
the this this this practice you describe
of
finding anicca in
yeah, in the situation you find yourself
in like yeah, you have to really dig.
um
It's not like pasting it. It's It's like
uh
basically it's like if there is if you
discern suffering or like greed, hatred, or
suffering or like greed, hatred, or
delusion more specifically in my
experience, then you
you're you're like digging to find where
is What am I ignoring basically? What is
Where is this
ignoring of anicca taking place? Uh
Yeah, cuz that's it. Everything would
fall down to that. You're either seeing
anicca or you're not seeing it, ignoring
it.
So, that's why it's often not
you know, figuring out how your
intentions come to be and what prompted
them. It's more like, what is the
presently enduring feeling in regard to
this presently enduring intention?
Cuz that's where your craving will be
rooted in.
And that's why often you'll be acting
out of those intentions, revolving
around them, having more thoughts. It's
because they happen to be pressuring you
and they're pressuring you cuz you were
unaware of the nature of those
phenomena.
It's always pain. It's always There's
always this
Yeah. Whether it's craving for pleasure
or Exactly. anger Presence of craving
means presence of suffering. To the same
extent craving is there to that extent
suffering is there.
It's not like sometimes craving
disappears but suffering stays. No,
literally, presence of craving is what
is felt as suffering from the point of
view of feeling.
Nothing else.
So, if you remove the craving as
present, there is nothing to be felt.
It's not like craving then produces this
process that results in suffering. No.
The four noble truths is the presence of
craving, presence of suffering. Absence
of craving, absence of suffering.
So, you want to then learn how to think
without a craving, act without a
craving, live without a craving, you
will then learn how to be free from
suffering perpetually.
And that's what the noble eightfold path
would be.
So, yeah, that disease that you
uneasiness that you discern
on account of anything that's presently
enduring, yeah. So, now you want to see
what is my attitude? What is my
intention? What is my current feeling in
regard to this uneasiness that I'm
discerning? Am I trying to get rid of
it? Because uneasiness in itself is not
Because uneasiness in itself is not
suffering.
Feeling in itself is not suffering.
Every feeling counts as suffering while
you're not free from craving.
But in itself, aggregated feeling is not
what dukkha is.
So, even that uneasiness,
it's only suffering cuz implicitly you
want to get rid of it.
And you're not seeing that
fundamental, subtle, yet kind of obvious
attitude that you know about, but you're
not seeing it in this instance, on this
level. It's not apparent to you.
Hence, suffering is there.
And there's always ignorance. There's
always some
some
ignoring taking place actively right
now. Like, unless you're
an arhat.
Uh
Well, yeah.
I think it's like what I said in in one
of those talks.
You know,
you have to learn like it's it's part of
the existence, part of the You can't
think about everything all the time.
It's impossible. Even the Buddha
couldn't do that.
You think about certain things, which
means other things must be
sort of forgotten at the time.
But it's when you are not free from
craving, that forgetting means ignoring.
When you are free from craving, that
forgetting is literally just forgetting.
You're not thinking about those things
specifically. But when you do remember,
you don't It doesn't come back with that
ignoring, with that layer of of of not
lack of understanding with it. So,
whatever arises is fully, clearly
understood when it arises through its own through
when it arises through its own through
its own enduring and manifestation.
So, ignoring is not is not this mystical
it's not this mystical thing that you
must I must find out things that ignore
that I ignore. Ignoring is that attitude
that you have right here and now, for
example, not being thoroughly clear
about the nature of presently enduring
feeling that you have on that on that
right level. Not of a specific feeling,
but presently enduring feeling, the mood
you are not clear about it. Which means
to the extent you're not clear about it,
to that extent there will be some
gratuitous resistance to it or in or or
leaning towards it. In other words,
craving will be there.
And and that and that clarity I'm
talking about it you must develop. It's
not on the level of figuring it out as
an idea, but it's clarity right here
right now on the level of your attitude
towards your own feeling.
Are you resisting it? Are you ignoring
it? Are you indulging it when it's
pleasant?
And that's something you need to learn
how to sustain
throughout the day.
That peripheral recognition of presently
enduring feeling of this kind or that
kind, doesn't matter. You're not trying
to get rid of it, you're not trying to
prolong it, and you're certainly not
trying to forget about it or ignore it.
You can forget other things if you want,
but not the things not the point where
things converge.
Not the mindfulness of your body, for
example. Like that's where these things
are reference points or anchors in
satipatthana, whichever way you want to
translate it.
When you say where they converge,
is it
meaning uh
uh
any sort of
proliferated manifestation? No, it means where things
manifestation? No, it means where things
meet.
So, you have this idea, for example,
this intention
that it's pressured you to do something.
Say it's an unwholesome intention.
Well, the craving is not in the
intention. Not in your action, so to speak, doing
Not in your action, so to speak, doing
acting out of intention. The craving is
that simultaneously present feeling with
that intention.
So, things meet there. So, on one hand, you
things meet there. So, on one hand, you
have one intention, but then you have
another felt feeling, and your craving
is basically on the level of the
feeling, not on the level of the
intention. But, they meet in that
feeling. So, you are acting very
clearly, very consciously,
and that's why craving appears to be
part of like in this intention, in this
thought, in this desire, in this product
of my action.
But, it's not. It's always on the in
this regard to how you feel, not what
you intend.
But, those things are inseparable.
Feeling and intention.
But, if you stop maintaining
craving in regard to your feeling,
then you can intend, you can feel, you
can perceive, and none of that will be
bundled and together with that craving.
So, the feeling will cease to serve as a
convergence point.
Only for as long as there is feeling,
they will be converging on the
Sorry, only as long as there is craving,
they will be converging on the feeling.
Things without craving.
Or in other words, that converging is
that pressure,
that contact.
Like sense of self. Or or not? Well,
that's all all comes out of it.
It's that basically direction that
craving craving gives you. Like, for
example, as I said, you discern the
phenomenon of of this universal
uneasiness, but you haven't discerned
the direction of your resistance away
from it, the direction of I I don't want
this. Yet, it's there with it.
Yet, it's there with it.
Met with it. The truth is there, but
it's there, and that's why you suffer.
Not because things are uneasy,
but because you keep trying to sort of
squeeze yourself out of it.
You want it to go away. You want to get
rid of it.
And that's why it's unpleasant, which is
why you want to get rid of it, which is
why it's unpleasant, which is why you
want to get rid of it. So it's another
vicious circle.
So this is essentially the sutra on the
two darts, isn't it?
Where it says that the uninstructed does
not know how to deal with unpleasant
feeling other than putting sensual pleasure over
other than putting sensual pleasure over
against it.
And then aggravating the whole
situation. Yeah. Yeah, so when he's struck with the
Yeah. Yeah, so when he's struck with the
first dart of uneasiness,
he's struck with the second dart of not
knowing the escape from that uneasiness,
as in he will be resisting it, and
that's the true suffering. The noble
disciple doesn't get the second dart.
So he has his uneasiness, but he's not
resisting. And because the uninstructed doesn't
And because the uninstructed doesn't
know the escape from it, the only escape
he knows is to then try to basically
cover it up with pleasure of any other
kind. And that's where sensuality is sort of
And that's where sensuality is sort of
uh intoxicating on two levels, not just
cuz it provides you with pleasure, but
it simultaneously masks the uneasiness,
covers up the pain, which is the only
way of you at the time
uh the only way you know how to deal
with the pain.
That's where sensuality needs to be
restrained first out of faith.
And then if you don't give in to
sensuality as a way of masking the fact
that things are universally uneasy,
then your attitude of gratuitous
attitude of resisting the uneasiness
will become apparent on the level it is,
not in theory.
And then when you That's when you don't
suffer and then you basically sensuality
becomes redundant. You don't need it
anymore cuz now you don't suffer to
begin with. You are not hit with that
like that the tone the tone of pain
that's been pulled out.
But it's the recognition of that that
uneasy feeling, pleasant feeling,
unpleasant feeling is not where the
craving is.
It's in your attitude towards presently
during feeling not oh I felt this thus I
crave not currently now while I'm
thinking or trying to figure this that
these things out
what is the presently during feeling
that's where the craving that leaning
towards direction or leaning away
direction or or basically turning a
blind eye direction will be maintained
and cultivated.
So that's why like developing
mindfulness that teaches you basically
how to
stop being absorbed in immediate objects
of your senses.
So that you can see what current feeling
cuz feeling is not in your senses not in
not in your sense organs not in in the
sense object.
It's pretty much as that background to
it as a context to the to those things.
So you want to learn how to
maintain the sight of that context on
that peripheral level.
That's when those interrogations we did
on YouTube like oh
how do I feel not theoretically not
abstractly while I'm asking the question
what is my current feeling what is my
current overall feeling enduring
okay not okay a bit of both
which one is it and then learn that it's
ambiguous to begin with but the more you
look in that direction the clearer it
will become not you will not make it an
object of your attention. It's going to
stay a feeling but now you cannot ignore
it. Uneasiness endures easiness endures
Uneasiness endures easiness endures
neither endures.
And that's sort of the first step
towards kind of uprooting that gradually
is leaning towards it when it's pleasant
and leaning away when it's unpleasant
that you are not even aware of yet
you're doing it.
But the only reason you're not aware of
it is because that whole dimension
that peripheral sort of context
hasn't been developed. The mind hasn't
been developed enough.
So this is then where the sensory
strength comes in. If there's no escape
from unpleasant feeling other than
sensual pleasure for the ordinary
person. Yes, sensory strength, yes, but
also see many people would be sensory
strength, but then they would
misunderstand the diamond meditation and
then their practice would be about
focusing on various objects of their
attention. Usually comes down to
focusing on the objects of your senses.
Whether it's the object of touch, my
body, whether it's sight, sounds, whatever
whether it's sight, sounds, whatever
else. And that's already the
the direction you will not discern
craving in.
That where you are focusing it's already
the product of you either leaning
towards pleasure or leaning away from
pain or ignoring the neutral feeling.
You can't make that feeling an object of
your attention in that sense.
It's always peripheral.
You will not find a feeling in your body
either. It's always fundamentally feeling every
It's always fundamentally feeling every
feeling as the sutta says, cetas it's
mental.
Now, would you say that when this when
feeling when vedana is discerned
peripherally by not running away from it
through sensuality then to see that
then to see that feeling arises in
dependence upon a sense base
and then to abandon then to abandon
sense base as
basically not mine. It It has been born
as we as we talked earlier, but I had no
say in that sense base being there.
Then, am I not pulling the rug away from
underneath the feeling and the
appropriation that goes with it?
Well, you you wouldn't you you you
wouldn't you can't just like abandon the
sense base in that sense.
So, if you're aware of the present
enduring feeling that makes you either
lean towards the sense base or try to
get rid of the things experienced
through a sense base or to ignore it.
Being aware of that feeling already, as
I said, already impedes that gratuitous
attitude of craving towards against or
or turn turning away from it.
So, if you sustain that, you will cease
to act out of senses. You will cease to
be bound by them eventually.
So, the product of your appropriation of
the the um appropriation of the senses
is a symptom of your craving in regard
to the feeling. It's not the problem in
itself. You do it only because you're already
You do it only because you're already
leaning away or towards your feelings.
But, as I said, they're invisible in
front of you. All you see is sense and
sense objects, like sense objects
really. You don't even see your sense
organs. And that's why immediate assumption
And that's why immediate assumption
that, "Oh, this is what I want and this
is what I don't want." That's why when
people suffer uh
ignorantly, the first thing they do is
they blame the thing that they perceived
that made them suffer.
Cuz they don't see that it's their
attitude in regard to how they felt when
they perceived that. That's where the
suffering is rooted.
So, if you say something that upsets me,
I blame you for my suffering.
And for as long as I don't look
basically peripherally from you, I will
never see the root problem of my
suffering. And same.
And same.
Like when there is a a prospect of
pleasure, I don't see it peripherally as
my attitude towards towards the towards
that agreeable prospect of my feeling,
I I see the sense organ or sense object,
sorry. So, I want that then.
So, I want that then.
And for as long as I don't learn how to
restrain and look beyond it while it's
still there, I will not see where the
problem is really rooted.
So, that's why it's not like oh, I
restrain, then I see my feeling, then I say no to
then I see my feeling, then I say no to
sense organs, then I have uprooted it.
No, no. I wasn't talking in such a way.
I know. But, it
it can sound like that if if you if you
set it up as this list, but the point is
if you see the context of your feeling
correctly enduring, you're already
withdrawn from your from the pull of the
sense organs. Even if there is still a
pressure there, the fact is you're
seeing more now. You're not rooted in
that pressure. So, if you sustain that
long enough, either through
contemplating impermanence of those
sense organs upon which your own feeling
depends, or the impermanence of the
gratuitous there isn't feeling that
you're leaning towards or against, you
will be removing the appropriation from
it. Yes, by seeing that I cannot be any
Yes, by seeing that I cannot be any
feeling without there being sense bases
as a Well, no. By seeing that
No, see you have no experience of no
feeling. So, what you just said would be
a pure abstraction. Oh, there can be no
feeling. That's inconceivable for you
how that would be without a feeling.
Instead, you want to see that whatever
feeling is there,
how has it arisen?
Can you even conceive how the feeling
comes to be, or you just find yourself
under it, so to speak, or affected by
it, or inside of you, whichever way you
find the feeling there, and you are not
privy to its origins, where it came and
how it came and why it came and where it
will go.
All you're privy to is the pressure that
it exerts over you.
And you perpetuate that pressure by
choosing to then engage with getting
more of that thing
that made you feel pleasant or trying to
get rid and get less of that thing that
made you feel unpleasant.
So, whatever feelings there, you want to
understand its owner nature thoroughly,
and you will stop leaning towards or
leaning away. You will stop trying to
get rid of it or or appropriate it even
more. And you will suddenly be unable to
ignore it ignore the nature of it.
Doesn't mean you need to constantly
think about it, but it means oh, when
when when you basically
recollect yourself upon the presently
enduring feeling
the true the nature that became apparent
of that feeling is seen with that
recollection. That's when things become apparent and
That's when things become apparent and
you understood the nature of it.
And that's when wisdom starts taking
place. That's why it's effortless. So,
that every time you feel you have to go
through these motions. You do that as a
part of training,
but if the understanding is taking
place, you will have to do it less and
less. And then eventually, when you recollect
And then eventually, when you recollect
the feeling, you recollect the true
nature of it. Means there is no room for
any craving to arise because the basis
for craving is forgetting, ignoring the
true nature of it, lapsing from it.
So, even when you're not thinking about
a particular feeling that's now
specifically enduring there in your
experience, that feeling is still
enduring there in your experience.
That's why you can recollect it. You can
go back to it.
So, when you go back to it, you want to
come back with as much wisdom that you
or knowledge understanding of it that
you develop beforehand, you want to come
back with it to it.
And see it clearly. That should be your
goal. Up until that whenever you think it, you
Up until that whenever you think it, you
think it's rightly.
No room for distortion anymore.
That it's arisen by itself.
It's there.
Being clear about the nature of a thing
being there to the extent necessary is
basically the fulfillment of
Satipatthana. He knows the body is there to the extent
He knows the body is there to the extent
necessary. He knows the feeling is just
there to the extent necessary.
Extent necessary for the final
knowledge. So, yeah.
So, yeah.
It's arisen on its own, all of that.
But, you want to see its there-ness, so
to speak.
That it's impenetrable to you. All you
can do is resist it
or lean towards it or ignore it. Nothing
else you can do about it.
It's impenetrable to any any of your
efforts. Everything is around it.
And that's the nature of any feeling.
Pleasant, unpleasant, or neutral.
That's the nature of any aggregate, for
that matter. It's un-ownable.
You said the uh all you can do is
lean towards it, lean away from it, or
ignore it. But, there must be an
alternative, otherwise there's no
freedom from suffering.
No. Alternative is to not lean towards it,
Alternative is to not lean towards it,
not lean away from it, and not ignore
it. Okay, so there is
Okay, so there is
Yeah, obviously there's other three
options. Well, no, that's one option.
Well, no, that's one option.
That's really
Four options, let's say.
No, you don't have four feelings at the
same time.
You only have one feeling.
Which means you're either leaning
towards, leaning away, or ignoring it,
which means you only have one option to
stop doing what you're doing at the time
towards that feeling.
So, when they asked the Buddha, "How did
you cross the shore?" because he said,
"If I kind of went against the waves, I
got tired. If I pulled backwards, I got
swept away. If I was uh trying to kind
of stay in the middle, I sank.
Oh, so Master Gotama, how did you cross
the shore? He said, "By not fighting the
waves, by not pulling backwards, and by
not standing still."
Which means at every given time, there
is one feeling enduring that you Yes, if
you try to understand it theoretically,
it's going to be a mind bog.
Oh, the three and the three and
I have to find this kind of basically
self-contorted position where I engage
in all these three aspects. That's
impossible.
No, it's recognition that there is only
one feeling at the time being felt.
Which means by default, you will either
be leaning towards it,
away from it, or ignoring it.
Which means that you only have one
option to not lean that Do not do that
which you're doing at the time,
whichever leaning that is.
And you cultivate that every single time
when there is a present enduring feeling
for the extent necessary for 7 days, 7
weeks, 7 months, 7 years,
the wisdom will have to arise.
Cuz you have basically been
preventing craving from from from
growing further.
Cuz as I said, craving, bhava, whatever
you want to take it, whichever aspect
you approach it with, needs maintenance.
Needs sustaining.
It's not a static thing in that sense.
So, how do I do all these things?
Discern as clearly as you can
peripherally what is the presently enduring feeling
what is the presently enduring feeling
mood you are under.
And then don't try to fix it, get rid of
it, explain it, find your craving in it.
Just try to not forget about it. Let it
endure while you don't specifically try
to think about it either. Like, "Oh, I'm
feeling like this. I'm feeling like
this." No, you are feeling like that
whether you say to yourself how you feel
or not.
So, the clearer it becomes on that
peripheral level, the less you will be
resisting it.
Because, again,
you are not doing the craving. Craving
is the result of you not knowing the
nature of feeling, for example.
So, you can't just stop craving as a
matter of choice.
But, you can remove the necessary basis
for craving, which is
lack of knowledge, ignoring, lack of
understanding, lack of clarity in regard to that which
lack of clarity in regard to that which
endures.
One way to
develop clarity in regard to that which
endures is
is it to
um
discern the sign the signs of the mind. So,
the sign the signs of the mind. So,
for example, yeah,
um
yeah, an angry or lustful um mind will
have Yeah, you can discern discern the like
Yeah, you can discern discern the like
discern the present enduring mood as a
phenomenon. Not as an object of your attention, but
Not as an object of your attention, but
as as a thing that endures there,
kind of
regardless of whether you attend to it
or not.
That's already kind of discerning the
shapes of your mind, the signs of it,
the characteristics of it enduring on
that general level.
Cuz the problem people have is even when
they get the idea, they used engaging
ideas only on the particular level. So,
I have to make it an object of my
attention. Ah, so that and then it
ceases you cease to be on the level you
must be, which is the level of present
enduring phenomena, which is always the
background.
So, you cease to be mindful, basically.
Mindful properly.
So, sensory strain needs to be guiding
or or rather guarding your behavior.
And then this is something within that
sensory strain, within unbroken sila as
seeing the danger in the slightest
fault. Within that now,
Within that now,
you start seeing the present enduring
mood, and you never cross the threshold
of acting out of sensuality and anger
and giving into the cause aspect, which
will kind of undo your work.
So, even if sometimes you're not clear
about it, you still have your sila
around as your guide.
And you don't do these things.
And then when the mind comes down, oh,
you get to rediscover that mood back on
when it's not as heavy, whatever
whatever pressure was exhibiting over
you. And that's how you train your mind
And that's how you train your mind
within that right context of sensory
restraint. And the more you do it, the clearer you
And the more you do it, the clearer you
become about it.
Which means less and less active
restraint you need to do.
Because there is the passion is
diminishing. Craving is diminishing because ignoring
Craving is diminishing because ignoring
is diminishing.
Until things become apparent to the
sufficient extent.
But it's a constant work. It's It's
absolutely nothing mystical about it.
It's just constant drilling. I remember
I mean, you probably heard me saying
that in other talks. When I started
reading the suttas, you know, you come
as a layman, just new to it. You have
some ideas, but a lot of it is unclear.
And you have these ideas of
enlightenment, and you know, if you do
these things right, enlightenment
happens to you, and then you're fixed,
and then you're always in the bliss.
But I remember I was puzzled by reading
the suttas, and it was the Buddha Oh, he
trains himself that And he keeps talking
about the training. And to me, that was
completely the opposite of what I
expected enlightenment to be. Like,
wait, how do you train that? It should
If it's the real thing, it should just
happen to you as like a you know, a
divine providence just sort of opens up
for you.
Not like training. Training is like
you're making it. And I was like, "Oh,
yeah, it's exactly that."
You're making your mind immovable in
regard to things that move you because
the mind is weaker than them. And that's
what the Buddha said in the sutras,
um
Arahant is not moved by his mind, it's
the mind that gets moved by the Arahant.
Like his thoughts, I'm not remembering
exactly, but it was the point is he's
not the one that moves.
The mind moves, not him.
Cuz he developed himself more than this
than his thoughts that used to move him
around.
So, he doesn't get overpowered by his
thoughts, he overpowers the thoughts.
Naturally. And that's all the similes like the
And that's all the similes like the
mountain and
uh earth, water, fire, immovable
regardless of what comes there to move
you. So, as I said, there's nothing mystical
So, as I said, there's nothing mystical
about it. It's just a constant work and
drilling on the basis of precepts,
seeing the danger and you read the
sutras and that's what the Buddha said
countless number of times.
Out of the man out of faith, young man
leaves his home, goes into homelessness,
dwells restrained by the rules of
Patimokkha, sees the danger in the
slightest fault, restrains his senses,
doesn't look for things that would
incite desire,
doesn't act out of anger, and then
spends his mind clearing it of the
unwholesome states.
Whether he walks, sits, eats, talks, he
doesn't tolerate the arisen sensual
desire, the arisen thought of ill will.
And even then, I remember reading it at
the first time, you think, "Okay, this
is all I'll do this, but then what do I
do for the actual enlightenment?" Cuz
you want something specific that will
result in this great experience. He's
like, "No, this is what you do."
But you just need to do it thoroughly.
And then you realize, "Oh, I don't
suffer like the simile of the the
carpenter using the axe handle."
He doesn't know how much his axe handle
has worn off when he uses it,
but it is wearing thinner each time he
uses it.
Until one day he comes into his
workshop, picks up the axe and says,
"Oh, my entire handle has worn thin. I have
my entire handle has worn thin. I have
to replace it."
And that's how the monk who purifies his
mind, one day he just recognizes, "Oh,
look, nothing for me to do anymore.
I am truly free."
And that's why, again, cannot be taken
away. It did not come through your senses. It
It did not come through your senses. It
did not come on the basis of any being,
anything happening to you out of your
control. No, it came on account of you
understanding the absolute nature in
that most universal sense of your
present enduring experience.
Not once, not twice, but thousands of
times. You trained yourself sufficiently.
And you said that
um
regarding feeling that the
the extent
to which
I either lean towards or lean away or
I'm ignorant about it
is
is tied to not understanding it.
Not understanding that presently
enduring feeling.
And I often read in the suttas that um
this understanding takes place by
directly discerning this present
enduring phenomenon like feeling that is
now there, that is now enduring.
there, that is now enduring.
And
then also discerning what it is
dependent upon, what it is
also there. That that will become
apparent. See, already, like, exactly, discerning
See, already, like, exactly, discerning
the present enduring phenomenon
can only be done on the present enduring
phenomenon. And that's that important
point distinction I was making where
where you end up thinking about the idea
that you assume feeling to be
as and you you assume it to stand for
the feeling, which means you're not
discerning it on the level of the
phenomenon. You're now just thinking
about your idea, which can only have
relative result, not the result of the
wisdom. So, it's that's like that's when the
So, it's that's like that's when the
experience is a whole where things
converge. If you go back to that, that's
where you would discern it. And that's
when it would become apparent.
Like, oh, it's dependent upon this. You
cannot have feeling without having this.
Either way, I am redundant. My sense of
ownership is there's no room for it.
Whether I ignore it or not, these things
don't know about me, so to speak. So,
me cannot I can only be affected by the
feeling. The It's not a two-way
relationship. It's only me who suffers
on account of feeling. Feeling is
unaware that I exist.
So, the more these characteristics
of the present enduring feeling are kind
of become apparent, the more dispassion
towards it you will experience. The less
ability to crave and lean to cuz you
always lean cuz you still assume you can
make a difference to it.
And you assume you can make a difference
cuz you're not clear about it.
Sorry? So, it's actually
So, it's actually
part of of one one single insight.
Yeah. Yeah. It It It's basically just
just just taking the same insight
further and further and more and more
things become apparent through the same
insight. Same The four noble truths is
just one noble truth.
It's the truth of suffering.
Presence of craving means presence of
suffering. That's the truth.
Through that truth, you know the absence
of craving means absence of suffering,
regardless of how disagreeable the
circumstances are.
Through that truth, you know then how to
sustain the absent craving. You know the
path. You know the way leading out.
But it's all 1 2 3 4.
It is one
different aspects of one then you get
through the other one through it's
through the same framework.
That's why somewhere somebody said that
uh the one who sees one of the four
noble truths sees them all actually.
Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah.
The one who understands basically the
principle of craving suffering suffering
craving understands the Arahatship.
So, when I discern a a presently
enduring feeling
I really discern it and
I also see that
I'm pressured by it
and that I can basically
do nothing about this feeling being
there and being pressured
about it and that my
my leaning away from it and my
my craving towards it and my my version
to and my ignorance is
basically just dependent upon not seeing
the presently enduring feeling.
That's what I mean. You you kind of you
end up sort of in a in a in a
like a little little irony of oh, you're
pressured by the feeling which is why
you give in to the thoughts of trying to
understand a feeling that is rooted in
craving that maintains the pressure.
But you do everything to be free from
the pressure.
But it has to be like that in the
beginning. That's what we meant craving
is to be abandoned by the means of
craving. So, yes, first you crave through your
So, yes, first you crave through your
thoughts to be free from craving and and
pressure of the feeling, but see
through developing more and more correct
mindfulness, you get to see ah, so I can
think these things without craving and
when there is craving I will not think
it. So, because of the previous cravings
in the past of wanting to be free from
suffering, now you actually ended up
practicing Dhamma correctly.
So, you abandon craving by the means of
craving. But not you abandon craving through
But not you abandon craving through
constantly engaging repetitively through
the same craving. No, you perpetuate.
So, you abandon craving through learning
how to not engage with craving anymore.
For which you had to crave initially to
that idea. I want ideal to develop.
Has to be affected with craving
initially and that's fine. But you want
to see through it.
Same with a conceit in that same suitra.
Conceit is to be abandoned by the means
of conceit. Such and such monk hears
that another monk became an arahant. He
thinks to himself,
"If he can do it, I can do it."
Really conceited thought.
Quite unwholesome.
But because of it, he actually starts
restraining more.
Starts reading the sutras more.
Starts really paying that attention to
what's happening in the background of
his mind.
And he approves the conceit eventually.
And there you go. He's free now.